<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The copie of a late decree of the Sorbone at Paris, for the condemning of that impious and hæreticall opinion, touching the murthering of princes generally maintained by the Iesuites, and amongst the rest, of late by Ioannes Mariana, a Spaniard: together, with the arrest of the Parliament, for the confirmation of that decree, and the condemning of the said Marianas booke, to be publiquely burnt by the executioner. Taken out of the Register of the Parliament, and translated into English.</title>
            <author>Université de Paris.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08926</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113998</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849226</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849226</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14364</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08926)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14364)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 728:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The copie of a late decree of the Sorbone at Paris, for the condemning of that impious and hæreticall opinion, touching the murthering of princes generally maintained by the Iesuites, and amongst the rest, of late by Ioannes Mariana, a Spaniard: together, with the arrest of the Parliament, for the confirmation of that decree, and the condemning of the said Marianas booke, to be publiquely burnt by the executioner. Taken out of the Register of the Parliament, and translated into English.</title>
                  <author>Université de Paris.</author>
                  <author>I. B., fl. 1610-1614.</author>
                  <author>I. W., fl. 1610.</author>
                  <author>France. Parlement (Paris)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By R. B[arker],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's preface signed "I.B."; additional matter at end signed "I.W.".</note>
                  <note>Texts in Latin and French, with English translation.</note>
                  <note>An attack on: Mariana, Juan de.  De rege et regis institutione.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ F² .</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A" with part of a woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mariana, Juan de, 1535-1624. --  De rege et regis institutione --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14364:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14364:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>COP<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> OF A LATE DECREE OF the <hi>Sorbone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> for the condemning of that impious and haericall opinion touching the murthering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; Generally maintained by the Ieſuites, And amongſt the reſt, of late by IOANNES MARIANA, a Spaniard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Together, with the Arreſt of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that Decree, <hi>And the condem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Marianas <hi>Book <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> burnt by the Executioner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Taken out of the Regiſter of the Parliament, and tranſlated into Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ IMPRINTED AT LONDON by R.B. ANNO 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preamble">
            <pb facs="tcp:14364:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14364:2"/>
            <head>THE PREAMBLE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath bene long ſince obſerued, that England whileſt it was in captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and bondage vnder the Biſhop of Rome, was of all other Countreys moſt oppreſſed with his intolerable exactions, and moſt heauy impoſitions. In ſo much as this our moſt noble Countrey was termed by the Frenchmen <hi>the Popes Aſſe;</hi> and one of the Popes owne Cardinals, in the dayes of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentius</hi> 4. vnderſtanding of the polling and pillage which the Romane Collectors and miniſters did vſe in this Countrey, to the great griefe of the inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb facs="tcp:14364:3"/>of, did in compaſsion vſe theſe wordes to the ſaid Pope, <hi>Anglia nostrís iniurijs mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toties laeſa, quaſi Aſina Balaam, calcaribus &amp; fustibus caeſa, tandem loquitur &amp; oblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur, &amp; ſe nimis &amp; intolerabiliter conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur fatigatam, &amp; instaurabiliter damnifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam;</hi> England many times wounded with our iniuries, and beaten as it had bene Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laams aſſe, with ſpurres and clubs, at the laſt doeth ſpeake and repine at it, and doeth complaine, that ſhe was too much and intolerably wearied, and irrecoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably damnified. Into which blockiſh thraldome this kingdome was brought, through the lewdneſſe, falſe practiſes, and impoſtures of the Prieſts, who by their counterfait miracles, and Reuelations, touching the ſeuerall paines and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſoules in Purgatorie, ſo terrified the mindes of men and women (brought vp in ignorance and more then Aegyptia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call darkenes) as they led them hither and thither like brute beaſts, for the compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of their owne deſignes, that they, and the Pope their maſter might tyrannize as
<pb facs="tcp:14364:3"/>they liſt. And although the iuggling and fraud of the Biſhop of Rome, and his traiterous brood, is now more publiquely knowen to all the world, and eſpecially to vs here in England, then it was in former times: Yet as if we meant to be Aſſes ſtil, it is incredible, how many are dayly ſeduced with toyes and bables by ſuch lewd Prieſts and Ieſuites, as hauing bene traiterouſly brought vp in the Seminaries beyond the Seas, and learned all the falſe ſleights and iuggling trickes that thoſe places can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, doe lurke, vpon their ſtealth into England, in many corners within this Realme, ſtudying with all their skill, not onely to imitate their Predeceſſors in all their wicked and lewd practiſes, but to goe therein farre beyond them; as being Vipers of a more deteſtable generation, then we euer heard of in this Countrey, or in any other Chriſtian Kingdome or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the dayes and times of our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And as it is obſerued by <hi>Philo</hi> the Iew, of the old Scribes and Phariſes before the comming of our Sauiour CHRIST,
<pb facs="tcp:14364:4"/>how mightily they preuailed and were followed by women; ſo now it hapneth and falleth out in this Kingdome with that ſexe, that theſe new Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes, the Ieſuites and Prieſts that adhere vnto them, doe ſtrangely bewitch them, hauing more ſecret conuerſation with them, vnder pretence of Confeſsion, then in ſome politicke conſiderations perhaps is conuenient. It is too well knowen to this falſe brood of Romiſh Prieſts and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, how eaſily, and by what light ſleights women may be ſeduced: neither are they ignorant, when they haue ſo done, what miſchiefe doeth thereby (for the moſt part) happen, in thoſe families, where ſuch ſeduced women doe liue and beare rule, they being commonly very paſsionate and violent in their affections and opinions. But it were leſſe hurt, if theſe new Scribes and Phariſes did limit their falſe practiſes to the inueygling and ſeducing of women, and that they did not in like ſort ſeeke with al their Engines and deuiliſh ſtratagems to infect with their
<pb facs="tcp:14364:4"/>poyſon young Gentlemen, and ſuch others of the Laitie, as they can by any meanes induce to giue eare vnto them; moſt men (not well grounded) being ſoone weary of the preſent eſtate wherein they liue, and euer deſirous of Nouelties, (eſpecially we in England,) if they tend to ſuperſtition and Idolatry: Whereby it falleth out, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature of peſtilent corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and poiſon, which worketh very vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently when it is taken, that the late ſort of Recuſants in England, men and women of all ſorts (which haue bene peruerted and poyſoned by the ſaid new Ieſuiticall brood, and other Impoſtors of their ſtraine) are growen into great fury, indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with no patience at all, to be in any wiſe impugned. For the more violent the poyſoned opinions are, wherewith they are peruerted, the more deſperate and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious they are become, to vphold and defend them. The <hi>Powder-Treaſon</hi> in England had many abetters; and that lewd Ieſuite <hi>Garnet,</hi> drawen and hanged for his Treaſon, is now become a Martyr,
<pb facs="tcp:14364:5"/>and wanteth not the confirmation of his Martyrdome by a ſtrange miracle in a ſtraw, deuiſed and publiſhed by two lewd Recuſants in London, one <hi>Griffin</hi> a tailor, and <hi>Wilkinſon</hi> a yong ſilke man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And it is not to be doubted, a Ieſuite very lately hauing written an <hi>Apologie</hi> in the behalfe of the ſaid lewd Traitor, (the ſame being approued by the <hi>Generall</hi> of the Ieſuites in Rome, after it was allowed by three other Ieſuites) but that our Recuſants in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of the furious ſtampe, will hereafter, as they dare, iuſtifie the ſaid villainous Traitour. When the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance <hi>Anno</hi> 3. <hi>Regis Iacobi</hi> was made and confirmed by Act of Parliament, it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably ſuppoſed, that all the Recuſants in England would willingly haue taken it, as ſundry of them began, had not the Ieſuits oppoſed themſelues, and procured the Pope to commaund the contrary. Since which time it is euident, how many haue refuſed, (as being bewitched and caſt into a reprobate ſenſe) to receiue the ſaid Oath, diuers euen of the more moderate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14364:5"/>ſort, as well Prieſts as other perſons, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that they cannot in conſcience receiue it, becauſe the trayterous poſitions concerning the depoſing or murthering of Princes by their Subiects (there being little difference betwixt them, in that it hath bene ſeldome ſeene, that ſuch tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Subiects as were able to depoſe their Soueraignes, did euer thinke it poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to ſuffer them to liue) are there termed to be <hi>Haereticall.</hi> Falſe and diabolicall aſſuredly they are, and directly contrary to the two firſt Commandements of the ſecond Table, <hi>Honour thy father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> and <hi>Thou ſhalt doe no murther;</hi> And then, if they haue bene wilfully and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely defended by any, why they ſhould not be acknowledged for damnable Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, I for my part cannot diſcerne. For I agree in iudgement herein with <hi>Grost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> Biſhop of Lincolne (in the dayes of <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. King of this Realme) where he defineth Haereſie in theſe words; <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſis est ſententia humano ſenſu electa, Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae ſacrae contraria, palam edocta, pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer
<pb facs="tcp:14364:6"/>defenſa:</hi> Haereſie is an opinion cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by humane ſenſe, contrary to the Scripture, publiquely taught, and wilfully defended. How theſe falſe lewd and traiterous opinions haue bene publiſhed to the world, and ſhamefully mainteined, it doeth appeare by diuers bookes and Treatiſes, printed and diuulged, to the perpetuall ſhame of the Authors and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouers of them: As by the booke intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>De iustâ abdicatione Hen.</hi> 3. and by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other not long ſince, Viz. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 13. <hi>An.</hi> 1598. allowed to be Printed <hi>In Coenobio Madriti,</hi> at <hi>Madrill</hi> in Spaine, by Friar <hi>Peter de Onna</hi> the Principall of that Order, and compiled by <hi>Iohn Mariana,</hi> a Spaniſh Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite, at that time Scholemaſter to the now King. This ſecond booke is thus intituled, <hi>Iohannis Marianae Hispani è ſocietate Ieſu, De Rege &amp; Regis inſtitutione libri tres ad</hi> Philippum 3. <hi>Hispaniae Regem Catholicum;</hi> Three books of <hi>Iohn Mariana,</hi> a Spaniard, of the ſocietie of <hi>Ieſu,</hi> Of a King, &amp; Of the inſtruction, or bringing vp of a King, to <hi>Philip</hi> the 3. the Catholick king of Spaine.
<pb facs="tcp:14364:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>And the Author of it hath the now Kings Licenſe, that none within his dominions vnder a certaine penaltie, ſhall print it, <hi>niſi de Authoris voluntate,</hi> without the Authors conſent. In this booke the murthering of Princes by priuate perſons, is in direct termes fully approued, and particularly the butcherous and traiterous ſlaughter of the French King <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. by <hi>Iames Clement</hi> a <hi>Dominicane.</hi> Againſt which traiterous, deuiliſh and hęretical doctrine, diuers learned men haue oppoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and lately the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris,</hi> vpon the barbarous murther of their late renowmed King <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. who beſides their deteſtation of that fact, do fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the ſaid new conceit of murthering of Kings and Soueraigne Princes, to be a very lewd and haereticall opinion. The Act of whoſe proceedings comming to my friends hands, together with the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning, drawing through the ſtreets, and burning of the ſaid booke of <hi>Iohn Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riana,</hi> he hath thought it fit to offer to
<pb facs="tcp:14364:7"/>the Preſſe to be publiſhed in Print, if ſo it might ſeeme good to ſome in Authority: to the end that thereby, if it were poſsible, not onely the malignant humours of the more furious ſort of our Popiſh Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, might be abated, when they ſhall finde their treacherous and traiterous ſchoolemaſters, the Ieſuites, with their adherents, to bee condemned for Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; but that alſo the milder and more moderate ſort of Prieſts, and other Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, might be induced not to refuſe the ſaid Oath of Allegiance, becauſe the ſaid conceits of murthering of Princes (a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent in effect of depoſing them) is therein termed an <hi>Haereticall</hi> opinion. And ſo I referre you to the Actes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as they were copied out of the Regiſter of the Parliament of <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14364:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ANNO DOM.M.DC.X.</head>
            <div type="Act">
               <p>CVM SACRA THEOLOGIÆ facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, ob feſta Pentecoſtes, &amp; Comitia priuata, inter viros ſelectos Ordinis Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiae, in preſenti negotio agitata, ſuos ſtatos &amp; ordinarios Conuentus prima aut ſecunda die Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nij habere non potuiſſet, illos in diem quartum Iunij transtulit, atque omnes Magistros Theologiae, in vim obedientiae, quam emiſſo ſacramento Facultati ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponderunt, in Collegium <hi>SORBONICVM</hi> conuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauit, vbi post Miſſam de Sancto Spiritu more ſolito celebratam, deliberârunt ſuper executione Senatuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſulti, cuius haec ſumma est.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vria Parlamenti,</hi> Decu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rijs, maiore rerum Capita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Edictivnd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatis, procedendo ad iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium &amp; litem capitalem, ac extraordinariam, Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris generalis Regis poſtulatione instructam, aduerſus nefandiſsimum, crudeliſimum, &amp; execratiſsimum parricidium, in ſacratam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonam
<pb facs="tcp:14364:8"/>
                  <hi>HENRICI 4.</hi> Regis patratum, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dito Cognitore generali Regio, decreuit, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> decernit, vt diligentia &amp; procuratione De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cani &amp; Syndici Facultatis Theologiae, eadem facultas quàm primùm conuocetur, ad delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum ſuper confirmatione Decreti praedictae Facultatis, quod die xiij. Decembris Anno <hi>M. CCCC. XIII.</hi> à centum quadraginta &amp; vno Theologis eiuſdem facultatis constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, dehinc Concilij Constantienſis authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate roboratum fuit. Quo Decreto definitur; <hi>Nemini licitum eſſe, quacun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> occaſione, cauſa vel praetextu quaeſito, Sacroſanctis Regum &amp; aliorum Principum ſupremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum perſonis vim inferre;</hi> Deinde, vt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretum quod in eiuſdem facultatis Comitijs ſtatuetur, omnium Doctorum, qui Comitijs &amp; deliberationi interfuerint, nec non etiam omnium Baccalaureorum, qui curſum Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicum decurrunt, ſyngraphis muniatur; Quò tùm demum, auditô ſuper eare Cognitore generali Regio, Curia decernat quod iustum &amp; rationi conforme erit. Datum in Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento xxvij. Maij, Anno Domini <hi>1610. Signatum.</hi> Voiſin.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14364:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>ITaque eadem ſacra facultas, vt mandato ampliſsimi Ordinis, tàm iusta &amp; neceſſaria praecipientis obtemperaret, primùm priuata, deinde publica habuit Comitia. Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans autem ſibi ex officio incumbere, vt ſuam Cenſuram &amp; Iudicium doctrinale cunctis il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud poſcentibus declaret, atque Pariſienſem Academiam à primis ſuis incunabilis paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem &amp; alumnam optimae ac ſaluberrimae Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinae perpetuo extitiſſe, &amp; tranquillitatem Reip. ab ordine, ordinem porrò &amp; pacem (ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum Deum opt. Max.) à Regum &amp; Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipum ſalute pendere; ac ſolius eſſe principis aut poteſtatis politicae, gladio vti; atque inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per paucis ab hinc annis nonnulla peregrina, ſeditioſa at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> impia dogmata inualuiſſe, quib. plerique priuati homines dementati, Sacro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanctos Reges &amp; Principes excrranda appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latione Tyranni contaminare, hôc<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nefario praetextu, necnon Religionis, pietatis, aut bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni publici iuuandi, vel promouendi ſpecie, in Sacroſancta Regum &amp; Principum capita conspirare, ſuaſque manus parricidas ſacro Illorum ſanguine cruentare, &amp; continuò pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiſsimam fenestram aperire non horrent
<pb facs="tcp:14364:9"/>ad perfidiam, ad fraudes, inſidias, proditiones, populorum interneciones, vrbium, Prouincia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ac Regnorum florentiſsimorum excidia, &amp; alia innumerabilia nequitiae genera, quae ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilia aut interna bella concomitari ſolent, haec demùm pestifera &amp; diabolica dogmata hodie in cauſa eſſe, vt qui diſceſsionem ab Eccleſiâ Catholicâ Romanâ fecerint, in ſuo errore ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureſcant, viroſque religioſos, Doctores &amp; Praelatos Catholicos, quanquam inſontes, quaſi talia docerent vel authorarent, fugiant &amp; detestentur:</p>
               <p>Eadem (inquam) Facultas haec &amp; ſimilia conſideratè perpendens, magna animorum conſenſione &amp; alacritate, ista peregrina &amp; ſeditioſa dogmata, velut impia, haeretica, ſocietati ciuili, paci &amp; tranquillitati publicae, ac Religioni Catholicae penitus contraria exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratur, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> condemnat. In cuius rei fidem, ac testimonium, Decretum antiquum ſibi de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegro renouandum eſſe duxit, quod ducentis ab hinc annis à <hi>141</hi> Theologis ſancitum fuit, in condemnationem huius execrabilis propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitionis.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14364:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <q>Quilibet Tyrannus poteſt &amp; debet licitè &amp; meritoriè occidi, à quocunque ſuo vaſſallo aut ſubdito, &amp; per quemcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> modum, per inſidias &amp; per adulatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, non obſtante quocunque iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento, aut confoederatione facta apud eum, non expectando ſententiam aut mandatum Iudicis cuiuſcunque.</q>
               <p>Haec aſſertio ſic generaliter poſita, &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum acceptionem huius vocabuli <hi>(Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannus)</hi> est error in nostrâ fide, &amp; doctrinâ bonorum morum, &amp; est contra praeceptum Dei, <hi>Non occides:</hi> &amp; contra hoc, quod di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit Dominus noster, <hi>Omnes qui gladium acceperint, gladio peribunt.</hi> Item haec Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertio vergit in ſubuerſionem totius Reipub. &amp; vniuſcuiuſque Regis aut Principis. Item dat viam &amp; licentiam ad plura alia mala, &amp; ad fraudes &amp; violationes fidei, &amp; iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti, &amp; ad proditiones, &amp; generaliter ad omnem inobedientiam ſubiecti ad Dominum ſuum, &amp; ad omnem infidelitatem &amp; diffiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian vnius ad alterum, &amp; conſequenter ad
<pb facs="tcp:14364:10"/>aeternam damnationem. Item ille qui affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat obstinatè talem errorem, &amp; alios qui inde ſequuntur, est <hi>haereticus,</hi> &amp; tanquam haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus debet puniri, etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſt ſuam mortem. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetur in Decretis xxiij. ix. V. &amp; Act. Anno <hi>M. CCCC. XIII.</hi> die Mercurij xiij. Decembris.</p>
               <p>Quae Cenſura Facultatis Pariſienſis in Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodo Constantienſi, Seſsione xv. Anno <hi>M. CCCC. XV.</hi> pridie Nonas Iulij, his conceptis verbis comprobata füit.</p>
               <p>PRaecipuâ ſollicitudine volens haec ſacro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſancta Synodus, ad extirpationem erroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; haereſium in diuerſis mundi partibus inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcentium prouidere, ſicut tenetur, &amp; ad hoc collecta est, nuper accepit, quod nonnullae aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertiones in fide, &amp; bonis moribus, ac multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter ſcandaloſae, totiuſque Reip. ſtatum, &amp; ordinem ſubuertere molientes, dogmatiſatae ſunt; inter quas haec Aſſertio delata est; <q>Quilibet Tyrannus poteſt &amp; debet licitè &amp; meritoriè occidi per quemcunque vaſſallu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuum, vel ſubditum, etiam per clanculares inſidias, &amp; ſubtiles blandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias
<pb facs="tcp:14364:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>vel adulationes, non obſtante quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque pręſtito Iuramento, vel confoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratione facta, nec expectatâ ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ, vel Mandato Iudicis cuiuſcunque.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Aduerſus hunc errorem ſatagens haec ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta Synodus inſurgere, &amp; ipſum funditùs tollere, praehabitâ deliberatione maturâ decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, decernit, &amp; definit, huiuſmodi doctrinam erroneam eſſe in fide &amp; moribus, ipſamque tanquam <hi>haereticam,</hi> ſcandaloſam, &amp; ad frandes, deceptiones, mendacia, proditiones, periuria, vias dantem, reprobat, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnat. Declarat inſuper, decernit, &amp; defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit, quod pertinaciter doctrinam hanc perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioſiſsimam aſſerentes, ſunt <hi>haeretici,</hi> &amp; tanquam tales, iuxta Canonicas ſanctiones puniendi.</p>
               <p>Sacra igitur Facultas ſtrictè, accurate<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, exploratis omnium &amp; ſingulorum Doctorum ſuffragijs, Primò ſtatuit antiquiſsimam illam Cenſuram Facultatis, Synodi Constantienſis ſanctione firmatam, non modò iterari, verùm etiam omnium hominum animis inculcari de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere. Secundò cenſet ſeditioſum, impium,
<pb facs="tcp:14364:11"/>&amp; haereticum eſſe, quocunque quaeſito colore, à ſubdito, vaſſallo, aut extraneo, ſacris Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum &amp; Principum perſonis vim inferri. Tertiò ſtatuit, vt omnes Doctores &amp; Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calaurei Theologiae, quo die in instituta &amp; Articulos Facultatis iurare conſueuerunt, in hoc ſimiliter Decretum iurent, ac ſyngraphae ſuae appoſitione obtestentur, ſe illius verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, docendo &amp; concionando, diligenter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicaturos. Quartò, vt haec Acta cùm La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinè tùm Gallicè typis mandentur, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgentur.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>De mandato Domini Decani &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crae Facultatis Theologiae Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſienſis, Signé DE LA COVR.</signed>
                  <signed>Collatione factâ. Signé. VOYSIN.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Eu, par la COVR, les Grand Chambre, Tournelles, &amp; l'Edict aſſemblees, le Decret de la Facultè de Theologie Aſſemblée le qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieſme du preſent mois de Iuin, ſuiuant l'Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt du 27. May precedent ſur le renouuelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:14364:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>de la Cenſure doctrinale de la dicte Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culté faicte en l'an 1413; confirmee par le S. Concile de Conſtance; Que c'eſt hereſie pleine d'impiete, de maintenir qu'il ſoit loi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible aux ſubiects, ou eſtrangers ſoubsquelque pretexte &amp; occaſion, qui puiſſe eſtre, d'atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter au perſonnes ſacrées des Roys, &amp; Princes Souuerains; Le liure de IEAN MARIANA, intitulé <hi>De Rege &amp; Regis institutione,</hi> imprimé tant á Mayence qu'autres lieux, contenant pluſieurs blaſphemes execrables contre le feu Roy HENRY 3. de treſheureuſe memoire; les perſonnes &amp; eſtats des Roys, &amp; Princes ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerains; &amp; aultres Propoſitions contraires au dict Decret; Concluſions du Procureur gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral du Roy; Lamatiere miſe en deliberation;</p>
               <p>La dicte Cour à ordonné, &amp; ordonne, que le dict Decret du 4. du preſent Mois de Iuin, ſera regiſtré es Regiſtres d'Icelle; ouy &amp; ce requerant le Procureur general du Roy; &amp; leu par chacun an â pareil iour, 4. de Iuin, in l'aſſembleé de la dicte Faculté, &amp; publié au premier iour de Dimanche es Proſnes des Paroiſſes de ceſte Ville, &amp; Faulxbourgs de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris: Ordonne, que le liure de MARIANA ſera bruſlé par l'Executeur de la haute Iuſtice deuant l'Egliſe de Paris. Et à fait &amp; fait inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitions &amp; defenſes a toutes perſonnes de quelque eſtat, qualité &amp; condition qu'elles ſoyent, ſur peine de crime de leſe Maieſté,
<pb facs="tcp:14364:12"/>d'eſcrire ou faire imprimer aucuns liures, ou Traité contreuenants au dict Decret, &amp; Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt d'Icelle. Ordonne, que copies collati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onneés aux Originaux du dict Decret, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Arreſt ſeront enuoyeés aux Bailliages &amp; ſeneſchauſſeés de ce Reſſort, pour yeſtre leues &amp; publieés en la forme &amp; maniere acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumee; &amp; outre es Proſnes des Parroiſſes des Villes, Faulxbourgs &amp; autres Bourgs, le pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mier Dimanche du Mois de Iuin. Enioint aux Baillifs &amp; Seneſchaux proceder a la dicte publication, &amp; aux ſubſtituts dú Procureur general du Roy, tenir la main a l'execution; &amp; certifier la Cour de leur diligence au mois. Fait en Parlement le 8. de Iuin. Mil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſix cent dix.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14364:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ COPIED OVT OF THE Acts of the Court of Parliament.</head>
            <div type="Act">
               <head>ANNO DOMINI 1610.</head>
               <p>THE SACRED FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CVLTIE OF DIVINES, not being able, by reaſon of the feaſt of Pentecoſt, and of ſome priuate meetings held touching this preſent buſineſſe by certaine ſelected perſons of that Order, to keepe their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall, and ordinary Aſſemblies on the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of Iune, aſsigned them ouer vnto the fourth of the ſame, and ſummoned by vertue of their obedience ſworne vnto that Facultie, all the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duats in Diuinity, vnto the Colledge of the SOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BONE. Where after celebration of the Maſſe <hi>de ſancto Spiritu,</hi> (as the vſuall maner is) they entred into conſultation touching the performance and execution of the Arreſt of Parliament: the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour whereof enſueth.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="document">
                           <p>
                              <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE COVRT, <hi>the Great Chamber, the Tournell, and the Chamber of the Edict beeing aſſembled, and proceeding to iudgement in the proceſſe criminall and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary,
<pb facs="tcp:14364:13"/>
                                 <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                                    <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                                 </gap>
                                 <pb facs="tcp:14364:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                                 <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                                    <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                                 </gap>
                                 <pb facs="tcp:14364:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>commenced and proſecuted at the ſuit of the Kings Attourney Generall, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the most barbarous, bloody, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable murther committed vpon the ſacred perſon of King <hi>HENRY</hi> the fourth, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being ſet foorth by the Kings ſaid Attour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, hath ordered, and doeth hereby order, that by the diligence and procurement of the Deane and Syndicke of the Facultie of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, the ſaid Facultie bee forthwith aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, to conſult together touching the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of a certaine Decree made the 13. of December 1413. by 141. Diuines of that Facultie, and afterwards ratified by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the Counſell of Constance. In which Decree it is defined:</hi> 
                              <q>That it is not lawfull for any man vpon what occaſion, cauſe, or deuiſed colour ſoeuer, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any violence againſt the ſacred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Kings and Soueraigne Princes.</q> 
                              <hi>Next, that order betaken, that what ſhall be decreed in the aſſembly of the ſaid Facultie, be confirmed by the ſubſcription of all the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and Bachelers now paſsing their courſe in Diuinitie, which ſhalbe preſent at the ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:14364:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>meeting and conſultation. That thereupon the Court, calling the Kings Atturney there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, may take ſuch courſe as ſhalbe agreeable to iustice and equitie.</hi> Giuen in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the 27. of May, AN NO DOM. 1610. Signed. <hi>Voiſin.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>WHerefore, the ſaid ſacred Facultie, for the performance of the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and commaundement of the ſaid Court in a matter ſo iuſt and requiſite, did firſt aſſemble themſelues priuately, and then in publique. And weighing with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues; That they were in duty bound to yeeld their opinion and iudgement in points of doctrine to whoſoeuer ſhould demand it: That the Vniuerſitie of <hi>París</hi> hath euer from her firſt original, bene the mother and nourſe of the moſt Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, and wholeſome doctrine: That the peace of a State dependeth chiefly vpon Order, and both order and peace (next and immediatly vnder God,) vpon the ſafetie and preſeruation of Kings and Princes: That it only appertaineth vnto the Prince and Ciuill power to vſe the
<pb facs="tcp:14364:15"/>ſword: That notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding within theſe later yeeres, certaine ſtrange, ſeditious, and impious <hi>Poſitions</hi> haue taken footing, whereby many priuate perſons beeing tranſported, feare not to ſtaine anoynted Kings and Princes with the deteſtable terme and ſtyle of <hi>Tyrants,</hi> and vnder this accurſed pretence, or by colour of furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or aduancing Religion, pietie, or the publique good, doe conſpire againſt the annoynted perſons of Kings and Princes, imbrewing their murtherous hands with their ſacred blood, and thereby opening a large window to all infidelitie, practiſes, treacheries, treaſons, ſlaughters of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ruines of Cities, Countries, and moſt flouriſhing kingdomes, and a thouſand ſorts of miſchiefes beſides, (the ordinarie attendants of Ciuil, and inteſtine warres:) and that laſtly theſe peſtilent and diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall points of doctrine, are the cauſe that ſuch as haue departed from the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Romane Church, are obdurate in their errours, ſhunning, and deteſting (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though without cauſe) other Religious
<pb facs="tcp:14364:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>perſons, and Catholique Doctours and Prelats, as if they were the Authors or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trones of thoſe opinions:</p>
               <p>Theſe and ſuch like reaſons the <hi>Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> maturely pondering, doeth with great vnanimitie of conſent and alacritie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſe and condemne the ſaid ſtrange and ſeditious opinions, as impious, haereticall, and moſt repugnant to Ciuill ſocietie, to the peace and good of the State, and to Catholique religion. In confirmation and witneſſe whereof, they thought it fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the ancient Decree eſtabliſhed two hundred yeeres agoe by 141. Diuines, in condemnation of this damnable Poſition: <q>That euery Tyrant may and ought lawfully and meritoriouſly to be murthered by any his vaſſall or ſubiect whatſoeuer, and by what meane ſoeuer, whether by treachery, or ſubtile inſinuation, notwithſtanding any Oath or promiſed Allegeance made vnto him, nay, not ſo much as expecting the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or warrant of any Iudge whatſoeuer.</q>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14364:16"/>
               <p>This Aſſertion being thus generally layed, and as this word <hi>Tyrannus,</hi> is or may be taken, is an errour in faith, and in the doctrine of good manners, being flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repugnant to that Commandement of God: <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill:</hi> and to that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Sauiour: <hi>That whoſoeuer ſhall ſtrike with the ſword, ſhall periſh with the ſword.</hi> The ſame alſo tendeth to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of the whole Common wealth, and of all Kings and Princes: giuing way, and free libertie to a world of miſchiefes, fraude, breach of faith and oath, treaſon, and in a word to all diſobedience of the Subiect towards his Lord, and to all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyaltie and diſtruſt of the one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and conſequently to eternall damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Whoſoeuer therfore ſhal obſtinately maintaine the ſaid error &amp; others therout enſuing, is an haereticke, and to bee puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed as an haereticke, euen after death. <hi>Let it bee recorded in the decrees</hi> 23.9. <hi>V. and dated</hi> 1413. <hi>on Wedneſday the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of December.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Cenſure of the Facultie of Paris was
<pb facs="tcp:14364:16"/>after ratified in the Councell of Conſtance ſeſſ.</hi> 15. <hi>on the</hi> 6. <hi>of Iuly,</hi> 1415: <hi>in theſe words:</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="document">
                           <p>
                              <hi>THis ſacred Synode hauing an eſpecial care (as in truth it ought, being to that purpoſe aſſembled) to prouide for the extirpation of all errours and haereſies, which haue ſet foote into diuers parts of the world, hath bene lately ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſed, that certaine Aſſertions haue beene publiſhed very ſcandalous aſwell in faith and maners, as ſundrywiſe elſe, and tending to the ouerthrow of the whole State and gouernment of the Common wealth, amongst which this is deliuered to be one:</hi>
                              <q>That euery Tyrant may and ought law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and meritoriouſly to be murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by any his Vaſſall or Subiect what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, either by cloſe treacherie, or by ſmooth practiſes, and inſinuations, notwithſtanding any Oath taken or promiſe of Allegiance made vnto him: nay not ſo much as expecting the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or warrant of any Iudge what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</q>
                           </p>
                           <pb facs="tcp:14364:17"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Againſt which errour this holy Synode ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſsing it ſelfe to make head, and vtterly to extinguiſh the ſame, after mature deliberation doth pronounce, decree, and define, that this doctrine is erroneous in faith and manners, and doth reiect and condemne it, as haereticall and ſcandalous, opening a gap to fraud, deceit, diſsimulation, treaſon, and periurie. It doeth moreouer declare, decree, and define, that they who ſhall obſtinately maintaine this pernicious doctrine, are haereticks, and as ſuch to be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, according to the Canonicall decrees.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Wherefore, the ſacred Facultie, hauing ſtrictly and carefully demanded the ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of all and euery of the Doctours, doth determine; firſt, that the ſaid moſt ancient Cenſure of the Facultie confirmed by the Decree of the Counſell of Conſtance, ought not onely to be renewed, but by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent iteration to bee imprinted in the mindes of all men. Secondly, that it is trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous, wicked, and haereticall, that any ſubiect, vaſſall, or ſtranger ſhould vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pretext whatſoeuer, offer violence vnto the ſacred perſons of Kings and Princes.
<pb facs="tcp:14364:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>Thirdly it decreeth, that all Doctors, and Bachelours of Diuinitie, vpon that day when they are accuſtomed to ſweare vnto the Orders, and Articles of the Facultie, they doe likewiſe ſweare vnto this decree, and by their ſubſcription promiſe, that they will in their Lectures and Sermons diligently ſet foorth the trueth thereof. Fourthly, that theſe Acts be publiſhed in Print, aſwell in Latine, as in French.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>By the direction of the Deane, and Sacred Facultie of Diuines at Paris. Signed <hi>DE LA COVR.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>Compared with the originall, Signed. <hi>VOISIN.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE being viewed by the Court, the great Chamber, the Tournell and the Chamber of the Edict aſſembled, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the Facultie of Diuines meeting together on the 24. of this preſent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of Iune, according to an Arreſt of
<pb facs="tcp:14364:18"/>the 27. of May laſt paſt, for the renewing of the cenſure and doctrinall reſolution of the ſaid Facultie, deliuered in the yeere 1413. and confirmed by the holy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Conſtance, that it is a very impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous haereſie, to mainteine it to be lawfull for Subiects or ſtrangers, vpon what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and occaſion ſoeuer, to attempt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſacred perſons of Kings and Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Princes: there being alſo viewed a certaine booke written by IOHN MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIANA, intituled: <hi>De Rege &amp; Regis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutione:</hi> printed aſwell at <hi>Mayence</hi> as elſewhere, contayning many deteſtable blaſphemies againſt the late King of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie memory HENRY the third; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt the perſons and States of Kings and Soueraigne Princes, and diuers other Poſitions contrary to the ſaid Decree: the Kings Attourney Generall hauing concluded, and the matter put to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation:</p>
               <p>THE ſaid Court hath ordered and doeth order, that the ſaid Decree of the fourth of this preſent Moneth of Iune,
<pb facs="tcp:14364:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhalbe regiſtred in the Recordes of the ſame, at the motion and requeſt of the Kings Attourney generall, and read yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on the ſame day of the 4. of Iune in the aſſembly of the ſaid Facultie, and that it ſhalbe publiſhed on the next Sunday in ſeruice time in the Churches of the Citie and Suburbes of Paris: It decreeth more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, that <hi>Marianas</hi> ſaid booke ſhall be burnt by the common Executioner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Ladies Church in Paris: and doeth inhibite and forbid all perſons of what eſtate, qualitie, or condition ſoeuer, on paine of high Treaſon, to write, or cauſe to bee printed the ſaid bookes or Tractats, being repugnant to the Decree aforeſaide, and to the Sentence of this Court. It decreeth, that copies examined by the originals of the ſaid Decree, and of this preſent Arreſt, ſhalbe ſent abroad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Balliages, and Shriualties, of this precinct, there to be read and publiſhed in the forme and maner accuſtomed; and moreouer in time of Seruice in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of all Cities, Suburbes, and other
<pb facs="tcp:14364:19"/>townes on the firſt Sunday in Iune. It enioyneth the Bailiffes and Shiriffes to proceede to the ſayd publication, and to the Deputies of the Kings Atturney gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to ſee to the execution, and to certifie the Court of their diligence in this behalfe. Giuen in Parliament the 8. of Iune 1610.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:14364:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat you be not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> of one particular occaſion of theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anas</hi> booke (which my friend in his Preface hath not touched) concurring with the generall deteſtation of that impious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of murther, the practiſe whereof wee haue ſeene vpon the perſons of two late Kings of France, HENRY the third and fourth: you ſhall vnderſtand that <hi>Rauillac,</hi> the villaine, who gaue that accurſed ſtroke, which hath made all France to bleed, being (as in his Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he deliuered) a long time in delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ere he could reſolue, that it was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to kill the King: falling vpon that booke of <hi>Mariana,</hi> he found his conſcience (as he ſaid) cleared of all ſcruple in that point, and himſelfe fully reſolued to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake
<pb facs="tcp:14364:20"/>it. And certainely the cordiall doctrine, which he from thence receiued, ſo ſetled his reſolution before hand, ſo ſteeled his heart in the execution, and after the deed ſeared and mortified his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in ſuch ſort, as that hee was ſo farre from any remorſe of the fact, as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and comfort therof ſeemed to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den him againſt all ſenſe of his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For being vrged by torture to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the trueth by whome he was ſet on worke, I will giue you a taſte of one or two of his confeſsions, as I receiued them from thence. At one time being examined vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the racke, who were his perſwaders to that accurſed deed: he deſired to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and hee would confeſſe the trueth: which being done, and he ſet on his feet, he ſtretching out himſelfe, tolde them: <hi>The trueth was, that now he found himſelfe at much more eaſe, then before, when he was on the torture.</hi> And this was all the trueth, he would at that time confeſſe. At ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time <hi>Preſident Iannin</hi> being appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to examine him, and preſsing him ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:14364:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtraightly to confeſſe, who had incited him to this fact: hee bad the Clerke ſet downe that <hi>Preſident Iannin</hi> had incited him therunto: who deteſting the villaines deſperate audaciouſneſſe therein: he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied againe; <hi>Well Sir, if I ſhould ſay ſo much at my death, I beleeue it would trouble you.</hi> Theſe things being aduertiſed from thence, I thought fit to impart vnto you, as arguments of the Caitiſes impenitency, and finall obduration, touching that exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable fact, grounded vpon the doctrine ſo condemned: the firſt ſparkes whereof being (as appeareth) kindled in France a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two hundred yeeres ſince, were then trode vnder foote by the <hi>Sorbone</hi> and the Councell of Conſtance: but ſince haue bene reuiued by the Ieſuites (the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious purueyours for the Popes Court) and by their Lectures and bookes nouriſhed and brought to thoſe flames that now wee ſee: as it hath beene not ſeldome obiected vnto them, but neuer yet by them wel denied; I am ſure the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine neuer publikely condemned by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:14364:21"/>reſolution of their ſchooles, as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and of late by the Colledge of <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone.</hi> So as whoſoeuer put the knife into the villaines hand, it is euident, that the mettall wherof it was made, (I meane the aforeſaid doctrine) was tempered in their forge, and their bookes (as it is confeſſed) gaue edge vnto it. Neither to ſay trueth, can it euer be imagined, that theſe wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſoules (ſuch as this <hi>Rauillac</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him <hi>Iohn Chaſtel</hi>) being perplexed in conſcience, and almoſt brought to the pit of deſpaire, with remorſe of ſome ſinnes of frailtie, durſt euer haue aduentured vpon a malicious and deliberate purpoſe of murther, eſpecially of their Soueraigne; had they not bene reſolued in conſcience by their ghoſtly fathers, (which office the Ieſuits haue almoſt ingroſſed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues) that howſoeuer it were a very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſinne to murther a priuate perſon: yet was it a merite, able to redeeme a world of former ſinnes, to kill a king, ſuch a one, as they ſhould point out vnto them. But whatſoeuer the ground may be, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:14364:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>it is, there is a very hard opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of them in <hi>France</hi> touching the late murther of the King, as may appeare by a briefe <hi>Paſquill</hi> ſet vp in <hi>Paris</hi> to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, the occaſion whereof was this. After the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> had ſtood a while bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the <hi>Arreſt</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> it is too well knowen how the late King (though againſt the generall wiſh of the whole State, and the aduiſe of many his loyall ſeruants) repealed that <hi>Arreſt,</hi> defaced the Marble Pillar, wherein their baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the cauſes thereof were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, recalled them home into his Realme (all men wondering to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it might be, vnleſſe it were to that, which ſince hath happened) tooke ſome of them too neere his boſome, and that he might aſſure (if it were poſsible) their loyaltie vnto him, erected for their ſocietie a ſtately Colledge in <hi>la Fleſche,</hi> the place where he himſelfe was borne. Theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious perſons, in exchange of ſuch his gracious fauours towards them, bare him likewiſe ſo zealous an affection, as they
<pb facs="tcp:14364:22"/>were neuer ſatisfied, vntill they had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his heart into their hands (the richeſt treaſure hee could haue endowed them withall) to initiate therewith the Chappel of their new erected Colledge. Which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obtained, and deliuered vnto them in a boxe of Siluer, layed on a pillow of red Veluet, they receiued with ſolemne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, to carry in triumph to their ſaid Colledge. At whoſe departure it is by the way reported, that a chiefe Preſident of <hi>París,</hi> let fall a queſtion vnto them, comming to take their leaue: Whether the Kings tooth which <hi>Chastel</hi> ſtroke out, were likewiſe encloſed in the boxe with the heart. This fauour of obtaining the Kings heart to burie in their Colledge, gaue occaſion (amongſt many other) of this Paſquill:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ce n'est, qu'a vous (trouppe ſacrée)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quo'n doibt bailler le Coeur des Roys:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quand les grands Cerfs ſont aux abboys,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>On en doibt aux chiens la</hi> Cureé.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14364:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>T'is you alone (you ſacred crue)</l>
                     <l>To whom the hearts of Kings are due.</l>
                     <l>When the great Harts are hunted hard,</l>
                     <l>The entrailes are the Hounds reward.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The riddle may perhaps ſeeme at the firſt ſomewhat obſcure, but I know you wil reade it without a Light. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſpare my paines to expound it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing already done more then I could well doe, to turne it in rime. And ſo hauing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted you with thoſe aduertiſements which came to my handes touching this buſineſſe, being certified hither by a very credible Author, which I haue to ſhew; I ceaſe to trouble you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
